<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The labyrinth the kingdom's in: with a golden threed to bring it forth into light, liberty, and peace agen. Being a brief but impartial history of the good and evil of the former, later, and present power of the nation, as it relates to God and the people. The result is a plea for the restauration of all in Christ (the kingdoms rest,) who is expected to appear more in the present, then in any former power of the nation. / By R. Bacon, a lover of mankinde.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Robert, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E541_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863903</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116119</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77067)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116119)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E541[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The labyrinth the kingdom's in: with a golden threed to bring it forth into light, liberty, and peace agen. Being a brief but impartial history of the good and evil of the former, later, and present power of the nation, as it relates to God and the people. The result is a plea for the restauration of all in Christ (the kingdoms rest,) who is expected to appear more in the present, then in any former power of the nation. / By R. Bacon, a lover of mankinde.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Robert, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, M.DC.XLIX. [1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb. 9. 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116119:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116119:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LABYRINTH the KINGDOM's in: With a <hi>golden threed</hi> to bring it forth into Light, Liberty, and Peace agen.</p>
            <p>BEING <hi>A brief but impartial History</hi> OF THE <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> of the former, later, and preſent Power of the Nation, as it relates to GOD and the PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reſult</hi> is a Plea for the Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all in Chriſt (the Kingdoms Reſt,) who is expected to appear more in the preſent, then in any former Power of the Nation.</p>
            <p>By R. BACON, a Lover of Mankinde.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Obſequium amicos, veritas odium parit. <bibl>
                     <hi>Terent.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Pet. 4.6.</hi>
                  </bibl> For this cauſe the Gospel is preached to them that are <hi>dead,</hi> that they might be <hi>judged</hi> according to men in the fleſh, but <hi>ſaved</hi> according to God in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl> If I build again the things I have deſtroyed, I make my ſelf a tranſgreſſor.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, M.DC.XLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116119:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116119:2"/>
            <head>TO THE High Court of Iuſtice, <hi>ſo called,</hi> Light and Truth, Mercy and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu are in your preſent proceedings a ſhadow, and but a <hi>ſhadow of good things to come, not the very things themſelves; not he that ſhould come, we are yet to look for another,</hi> even <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf the true <hi>anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that <hi>ſhall not,</hi> as you, <hi>judg</hi> according <hi>to the ſeeing</hi> of the <hi>Eye,</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> of the <hi>Ear,</hi> but he ſhall do <hi>righteous Judgment</hi> upon you, as well as others; I mean, not upon King <hi>Charles</hi> for All, but King <hi>Lucifer</hi> in All, King, Parliament, Army, All. This is and hath been the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>bottomleſs pit,</hi> who hath let in all manner of devils into the Nation to be the torment and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it; his <hi>name is</hi> therefore in the <hi>Hebrew tongue, ABAD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON</hi> but in the <hi>Greek tongue</hi> hath his <hi>name APOLLYON,</hi> and is indeed the great Deſtroyer of all Good in You, and the whole Kingdom: I give my vote to the ſlaughter of <hi>this King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but two things more to ſay to You (and ſay it I may (I hope) without offence, for I intend none, neither do I ſay it after, or to ſerve, or pleaſe, men, but God,) as they ſaid to Chriſt, By <hi>whoſe Authority do you</hi> do theſe things? or <hi>who gave you this Authority?</hi> or as Chriſt ſaid to them of <hi>John,</hi> Is it <hi>from heaven, or of men?</hi> If You ſay, it is <hi>of men,</hi> then you your ſelves are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116119:3"/> witneſſes againſt your ſelves, that you tread in the ſteps (<hi>i. e.</hi> are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the <hi>ſame principle</hi>) of thoſe that went before you, and do as they did, judg that evil in others, which you have not yet over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>(in the principle of it)</hi> in your ſelves: Let therefore he that is among you, without <hi>this fault,</hi> throw the firſt ſtone. But if you ſay, <hi>it is from Heaven,</hi> let it appear by your <hi>doing the works of your father which is in heaven:</hi> This we will beleeve, when we ſhall ſee you do that which none others did before you, that is to ſay, when you ſhall <hi>do good for evil;</hi> not only <hi>love thoſe</hi> that love <hi>you,</hi> but thoſe too <hi>(not their evil)</hi> that hate you, and despite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſe you: Let <hi>your rain</hi> of goodneſs <hi>deſcend,</hi> and your <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs ſhine,</hi> upon the Juſt, for their <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and the <hi>unjuſt,</hi> for their <hi>Clarification,</hi> and <hi>Reſtoration:</hi> Then ſhall we ſet to our ſeal, that you are that you expect to be,<note n="*" place="margin">As Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus was ſaid to be.</note> 
               <hi>The Chriſt of God,</hi> the <hi>anointed of the Lord,</hi> for the ſaving, healing, and reſtoring of the Land; to which God and all good men ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The aberrations from, and the walking after, the light of this <hi>ſtar,</hi> this <hi>anointing,</hi> by <hi>King, Parliament, Army,</hi> is the ſubject of this Diſcourſe, with all Chriſtian ſubmiſſion, put into your hands,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>R. BACON, Who, in his ſphere, ſeeks the good of all.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:116119:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Labyrinth</hi> the Kingdom is in; With a golden Threed to bring it forth into LIGHT, LIBERTY, and PEACE agen: Being an impartial Hiſtory, of the Good and Evil of the former, later, and preſent Power of the Nation, as it relates to God, and the People.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the height, and fall of the King, and his Party, together with the cauſe, and manner how.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo is his title, at leaſt ſo it was in times paſt, being through Flattery, Oppreſſion, Superſtition, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the like, lifted up in himſelf and over the Nation, and all orders and eſtates of men, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences therein; yea, above all that was, or is, truly <hi>called God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men; ſo that he ſaid in his heart, and all that were height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by, and took up their reſt in, this great and tall Cedar, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> did, <hi>I will aſcend above the heights of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116119:4"/> the cloude; I will be like the most high:</hi> that is, as wiſe, as ſtrong, as great as he: Or as did that other great and mighty Poter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate, we read of in <hi>Daniel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> reflecting upon his own glory, and the works of his own hands, boaſted himſelf before God and men, ſaying interpretatively, and in the account of both, <hi>Is not this great Babel, which I have built, for the honor of my Majeſty? for the ſpreading of my glory, and for a laſting reſt, and tabernacle to me, and mine to all future ages?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. No ſooner was this, thus in his ignorance of God, gone forth of the mouth of him, and his, but there apeared written upon the wall of this his, and their ſo great, but carnal Confidence, by the inviſible and irreſiſtible hand of God, (which only then, and now, the <hi>Daniels</hi> of the Kingdom were able to read and interpret,) MENE, MENE, TEKEL UPHARSIN. This is now not only Prophetically, but that which is come to paſs, eaſily to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by every one that paſſeth by, or goeth in and out, this Kingdom; ſo that every man may ſee, and underſtand this to be the interpretation of the thing, or hand writing. <hi>Mene,</hi> God <hi>hath numbred thy Kingdom</hi> (taken a note of all the particular vanities, follies, cruelties therein,) <hi>and finiſhed it,</hi> in reſpect of the glory, pride, and vanity, it now is, and hath been in. <hi>Tekel,</hi> Thou <hi>art weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in the ballances</hi> (of God and man) and <hi>art found too light. Peres, diviſit,</hi> God hath divided it from thee, and thee from it; or divided it into ſeveral peeces, and ſmaller parts and parcels: ſo that one hath one part, and another hath another: Firſt, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> take one peece; then the <hi>Scots</hi> take another; and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> take the laſt, or rather the firſt and beſt, and they too, divide it among themſelves, and ſtrive who, ſhall have the better part, or the whole of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. Thus the King, in this way and confidence of his, and thoſe that had ſtretched themſelves with him, upon this bed of reſt, which they have now found, by woful experience, is too ſhort for them; I ſay he and they have found that come upon them (at the Call and Command of God) which ſometime the Land of <hi>Judah</hi> did, yea, that very voyce of God hath thundered in their ears, houſes, and among their friends and eſtates, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116119:4"/> did among that people, and that in theſe very words, or to this very purpoſe, <hi>He,</hi> the Lord hath, <hi>lifted up an Enſigne</hi> (for God ſet up his Standard firſt againſt the King, before the King (in a way of open War) ſet up his Standard againſt the Parliament, or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ople; the Enſigne is lifted up of God, and given for a ſigne to the Nations; firſt, to the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> then, to the <hi>Scots;</hi> and laſtly (though not firſt in a way of open War) to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> all of them ſtanding ſtill in times paſt, and ſo ſeeming (as to the ſhaking of the Kings reſt and glory) <hi>afar off,</hi> (though ſome keen and quick-ſighted men had a view in God, of all this before it came:) they all obey his Call, and come forth againſt him and his with exceeding ſpeed, God ſaying of them, <hi>none of them ſhall be weary, nor ſtumble among them;</hi> none ſhall <hi>ſlumber,</hi> or <hi>ſleep; neither ſhall the girdle</hi> of their <hi>loins be looſed,</hi> till they have brought to paſs his <hi>Act,</hi> his <hi>ſtrange Act,</hi> nay, not ſo much as the <hi>latchet</hi> of their <hi>ſhoes be broken,</hi> to ſhew that all lets and hinderances ſhould be taken out of the way, that the Councel of God might take place, <hi>whoſe arrows are ſharp,</hi> every one piercing to the heart of King, Queen, Biſhops, &amp;c. <hi>and all their bows bent,</hi> men ſtill in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to ſecond and ſupply one affrightment with another: <hi>their horſes hoofs ſhall be,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>counted like a flint,</hi> that every march and preparation of calamity againſt him might ſucceed; the wheels of their Carriages and Ammunition like whirle-winde, all being always in a readineſs to annoy him. <hi>Their roarings ſhall be like a Lion,</hi> (as the King hath found,) <hi>they ſhall roar like young Lions; yea, they ſhall roar, and lay hold of the prey,</hi> and ſhall <hi>carry it away ſafe,</hi> and <hi>none ſhall deliver it;</hi> as it hath come to paſs in all thoſe great Engagements that have been againſt the King; and therefore ſaith the Text, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 5. Verſ. 30. <hi>In that day they ſhall roar againſt them like the roaring of the ſea,</hi> (againſt the prevailing, mighty, proud waves thereof there is no ſtanding out;) And if <hi>one</hi> of that way, or that engagement, <hi>look unto the Land,</hi> or any part of it, <hi>behold darkneſs and ſorrow, or diſappointment, and the light</hi> of this Kingly glory, or glorious Kingdom, oppoſed now to the Coming, and Kingdom of God (which yet they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in blindneſs, and in a way of tradition, prayed for,) I ſay all that light and glory is <hi>darkened,</hi> and eternally ecclipſed <hi>in the heavens thereof,</hi> that is to ſay, in the firmament of it, which was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116119:5"/> the perſons of the King, Queen, Nobles, and all thoſe either birds or beaſts, that had taken up their ſhelter under the ſhadow of this great tree, which by the Commandment of the <hi>Watcher,</hi> or ſtrict Obſerver of all things and Kingdoms, even the holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that for <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſake, never <hi>ſlumbreth</hi> or <hi>ſleepeth,</hi> is now felled down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. The King, to prevent, or rather to occur, and make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt this inundation, or flood of Fears, and troubles, flowing in upon him, threatning the overſhadowing, yea the total ruine of this Babel, that was ſo glorious in his, and others eyes, endeavours firſt the upholding it with the wit and policy of his Friends and Favorites, and his own perſonal affronts, and diſcountenancing, yea, openly, as in the Parliament Houſe, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing, eſpecially the heads of that party, or ſort of men, from whence his expectation of fear did come; but though this was effectual, to the caſting down many Stars, that ſeemed to be more fixed in the Firmament of the Peoples expected Rights, and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; yet the oppoſition, made againſt the other, was ſo far from blunting the edg of their affections, then, to the Publique, and proceedings againſt the corrupt intereſt of the King and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c. that they by oppoſition multiplied, and were ſo much the more fortified, and united againſt him; ſo that theſe <hi>bricks</hi> of policy, and ſwordleſs, or bloodleſs oppoſition, made againſt the Power prevailing againſt, and feared by the King, being <hi>fallen down:</hi> He ſpeeds into the North, and there is reſolved to <hi>build with hewen ſtones,</hi> and though the <hi>Sycamores</hi> had failed him, and his hope in them, yet now mindes to make further tryal, and <hi>change them into Cedars;</hi> ſets up his Standard, and makes Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among the Gentiles, men of looſer and more apparent, corrupt, and evil lives, and ſo appearing more remote then others from the knowleg and fear of God, and thus calls upon theſe Mountains to <hi>cover him from the wrath of the Lamb,</hi> who now appeared to ſit on the throne of God againſt him; to theſe in all Countries he ſays, <hi>Prepare ye War, wake up the mighty men</hi> in all parts; <hi>Let all the men of War draw neer,</hi> to the King, and come up to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: <hi>Beat your plow-ſhares into ſwords,</hi> your <hi>pruning hooks into ſpears: Let the weak ſay, I am ſtrong:</hi> Let none deny his aſſiſtance of Mony, Plate, Horſe, Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116119:5"/>§. 5. Thus the King, and all the fading, worldly glory, and creame of the Nation, being embodied into a potent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Army, marches up and down like a <hi>ſwift Dromedary, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing her waies,</hi> or as the ſame Prophet ſpeakes, like a <hi>wild Aſſe Colt uſed to the Wilderneſſe,</hi> which no hand had yet med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with, and therefore <hi>ſnuffeth up the wind at her pleaſure,</hi> or according to the deſire of her heart, as though none could turne her out of the way, <hi>ſo that all they that go to ſeek her</hi> for the uſe of man, do even make weary themſelves, as though it were bootleſſe to purſue after her any more; as was indeed the caſe of the King, and thoſe with him, who had led at ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times after ſo many fights, and frights, his and their purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (as they ſay,) ſuch a dance, that they were weary and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and even ready and upon the matter willing to give over; they ſaid once and agen as <hi>David, We ſhall one day periſh by the hands of this Saul,</hi> the fierce and firſt King of that, but (as ſome ſay) the laſt of this our <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but as the wild Aſſe is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and made tame in <hi>her moneth,</hi> ſo that a child may lead her, ſo after a while this Army, and mighty gathering together of men of Warre, become bedrid, and are <hi>taken as a wild bull in a net;</hi> ſo that to <hi>every child</hi> is now given <hi>to play on the hole of this Aspe,</hi> and the <hi>weaned child,</hi> to put <hi>his hand on this Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice den.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">§. 6.<note place="margin">A digreſſion, by way of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for the many ſlain.</note> Which though I ſo expreſſe in the language of the Scriptures, they being ſuch to ſome upon a true account, yet I acknowledge them upon another, to be men of might, and great renown, and therefore am ſo far from writing this as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing at their fall, that I hardly do it but with weeping eyes, and a heavy heart, and am ready to lament with <hi>David</hi> over them as he did over <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> his ſon, <hi>The beauty of Iſrael is ſlaine</hi> upon the <hi>high places, how are the mighty faine, tell it not in Gath, publiſh it not in the ſtreets of Askhelon, leſt the daughters of the Philiſtines rejoyce. Ye Mountaines of Gilboah</hi> (ye the ſeverall places, Cities, Hills, Plaines, and Valleys) <hi>let there be on you no deaw, neither let there be raine any more upon you,</hi> that there ſpring not up from you, by vertue of any moiſture, or bleſſedneſſe upon you from above, as it were from the ſeeds of the many ſlaine upon you, to beget a reſurrection of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116119:6"/> Warre; and the like dreadfull ſlaughter of men, and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, <hi>the flower</hi> of this Nation, <hi>For how were the mighty ſlain there in the midſt of Battell. O Jonathan,</hi> thou noble <hi>Brookes,</hi> thou noble, but miſguided <hi>Faulkland,</hi> how waſt thou ſlain! and many others, famous in their Generation, both on the one ſide and on the other, how were and are the mighty fallen, <hi>and the Weapons of Warr periſhed!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. But to return; after ſome few yeares, and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, this Mountaine of pride, oppreſſion, vaine-glory, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and cruelty, is melted with the blood of thoſe many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſlaine, <hi>for it is the day of the Lords vengeance, and the year of recompences for the controverſies of Sion;</hi> And therefore it is as to them and the Kingdome they ſought to uphold, <hi>that the ſtreames thereof,</hi> that is to ſay, all the means of their refreſhing, <hi>is turned into pitch, and matter,</hi> and fuell only fit and prepared for the <hi>fire,</hi> and this fire ſhall not be <hi>quenched night nor day,</hi> but <hi>it ſhall burne continually, yea the ſmoak thereof ſhall go up for ever and ever, from Generation to Generation, it ſhall be waſt;</hi> it ſhall never again be called from the dead, none ſhall paſſe thorough it any more, it ſhall only <hi>be for the Cormorant and the Bitter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, the Owle alſo and the Raven ſhall dwell there; for God bath ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out upon it the line of confuſion, and the ſtones of emptineſſe; they ſhall call for the Nobles thereof</hi> to come to the ſupport of this Kingdome, but <hi>none ſhall be there,</hi> and all <hi>her Princes</hi> ſhall be and are become <hi>nothing. Thornes ſhall come in their Pallaces:</hi> they ſhall afford them nothing but vexation, yea there ſhall be found in them, and in their Land of delight, only ſuch of the creatures <hi>Ziim</hi> and <hi>Jiim,</hi> the <hi>Satyres,</hi> the <hi>Vultures</hi> and the <hi>Owle,</hi> whoſe place is the Wilderneſſe and deſerts not inhabited: thoſe <hi>Puritans</hi> and <hi>Roundheads,</hi> of whom before there was little or no appearance in the Land, for their abiding was as it were in the Wilderneſſe, and their preſence was as ſtrange as gaſtly, and as much affrighting in times paſt to the multitude, eſpecially to the rulers of the Nation, as are thoſe birds and beaſts that dwell in ſuch ſolitary places, to ſuch as are unacquainted with them: ſo that the Wilderneſſe and the ſolitary place, ſuch was the ſtate of thoſe rejected by the King and Biſhops, ſhall be glad for them, and that deſart ſhall rejoyce and begin to bloſſome as a roſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116119:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the corrupt principles of the King &amp; Biſhops begin to fructifie, and ſpring up againe in the Parliaments and Synods of both Kingdomes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">§. 1. BUt to take up all (I intend) as I go. This roſe began firſt to be nipt in the bud, even before the forenamed deſolation of the forementioned State of men came to that height, both intended of God (though not then purpoſed of men) and ſince accompliſhed, and brought to paſſe through the over-ruling power of God, by men: And that after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and on this wiſe: that <hi>old Serpent</hi> the <hi>Divell</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> the head even of the King and his Biſhops, or followers, reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the whole, though not all the particulars or wholly, being now by the mighty hand of God, wonderfully <hi>bruiſed</hi> and broken, and laid even halfe dead, as a hopeleſſe, uſeleſſe, hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thing, which thing came to paſſe about the time of the Kings eſcape from Oxford to the Army in the North, and this came to paſſe thus, the <hi>old Serpent,</hi> of which I made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion even now (not intending the Kings perſon, which I did reverence and love, but the evill raigning in him, and others of his ſide and way, which I make mention of by the way, that I may not provoke any man, profeſſing my ſelfe one that ſeekes unfainedly the good of all) broods as I may ſo ſpeak, upon the ſeeds of it, both in the Scots, and Engliſh Parliaments &amp; Armies, ſo that it might be ſaid to the better part of both, that ſought after freedom and reſt in God in the Land, in truth, and thought that that had been the time of their joy, and reſt, yet there was ſaid to them, as to the <hi>Palestine</hi> of the Weſt, as in the Prophet <hi>Eſa.</hi> ch. 14. 29. <hi>Rejoyce not thou whole Paleſtine</hi> (though ſome of them did) <hi>becauſe the rod of them that ſmote thee is brok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, for out of the Serpents root, ſhall come</hi> forth a <hi>Cockatrice</hi> (or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> or the ſerpent renewed) <hi>and his fruit ſhall be a fiery flying ſerpent,</hi> more ſubtill, ſwift, fierce, or as the Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pture ſpeakes, the <hi>peircing Serpent,</hi> even <hi>Leviathan</hi> that crooked, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>very waies turning ſerpent, lifting up his head, and living again e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our boſome, the Parliament; For being even to death nipt with the froſt, and cold, the Winter of adverſity, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116119:7"/> of the King and Biſhops, is now taken by theſe mercileſſe, mercifull men into their boſome, where receiving warmth and ſtrength, he begins to grow ſtrong and vigorous, not only in them, but to live and riſe again in them, the Kings owne party in whom he ſeemed as to outward hurt, and appearing to be wholly exhauſt of life and being, ſo that this laſt deceipt or Serpent became more deceiving and pernicious then the former, yea the <hi>Serpent</hi> is now turned <hi>Dragon;</hi> every Dragon is a Serpent, but every Serpent is not preſently a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, the Dragon then is <hi>Serpens annoſus,</hi> the old Serpent, though in a new skin, a new and another better, though a more decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving appearance, as having eaten up other Serpents, a deceipt that hath (to make it the more deceiving) ſwallowed up into it ſelfe all other more groſſe, and now diſcovered deceipts, and therefore the more likely to deceive, even as an Angell of Light in the Parliament, and thoſe of their ſide, though in thoſe of the other party, like a <hi>Lion,</hi> or a <hi>Bear robbed of her whelps,</hi> or kept long in hunger, as thoſe were, that were made ready to devoure <hi>Daniel,</hi> that they might with greater ravening and appetite, fall againe to, and upon their deſired prey.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. To all which they were prepared, and made ready, by the Scots complying, and <hi>committing whoredome</hi> with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt principles of the King and Cavaliers, contrary to their Oath, Covenant, and firſt Engagement; yea, the whole Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Order, Scotch and Engliſh (that I ſpeak nothing of the Independent for the preſent) like <hi>Ahola</hi> and <hi>Aholibah,</hi> ſhe ſo <hi>diſcovered her whoredomes,</hi> and <hi>her nakedneſſe,</hi> that the <hi>mind of God</hi> himſelfe is wonderfully, and apparently <hi>alienated</hi> from her, like as it was from the Epiſcopall, her elder and firſt rejected ſiſter, I ſay firſt rejected, out of the bed of God; for they like a woman prone to Adultery, have multiplied their whoredomes, in calling to remembrance the dayes of their youth, wherein they all knew themſelves, and others know it of them, that they had plaid the <hi>harlot</hi> in <hi>the Land of Aegypt,</hi> in the ſtate of Egyptian darkneſſe, in the Biſhops dayes, wherein they bowed the knee to the ſame Idolls they did; ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116119:7"/> that they <hi>have doted, every one upon their paramore of Aegypt,</hi> whoſe <hi>fleſh,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeakes, is as the <hi>fleſh of Aſſes,</hi> and whoſe <hi>iſſue</hi> is as the <hi>iſſue</hi> of <hi>horſes,</hi> that is, that which to the full gives content to the unſatiable appetite of carnall and corrupt principled profeſſors; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their great pretence of Religion, and Reformation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend nothing but the <hi>waſhing of the outſide of the cup and platter,</hi> and under a pretence of <hi>long prayer,</hi> and ſtrict government, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure widdowes houſes,</hi> loving one part of them to be called <hi>Rabbi,</hi> another domination or tyranny of another kind: buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſetting up (like <hi>Jeroboam</hi> that made <hi>Iſrael to ſinne</hi>) two <hi>Calves,</hi> gilded indeed with <hi>gold,</hi> having for it a glorious pretence of holineſſe, and conformity to the Scripture, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing might come forth from them in the name of <hi>jus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum;</hi> theſe they ſet up in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan</hi> being in ſignification, the place of judgment. <hi>Bethel</hi> the houſe of God.</note> one in the place of common juſtice, corrupting the very principles, and glory of a true and right Magiſtracy, the other in <hi>Bethel,</hi> called the Church or houſe of God, being nothing elſe but a dead, woodden, weak, worthleſſe Idoll, yet done over all with gold, intitled in all the pieces and parcells of it (<hi>Directory</hi> for <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith, Forme</hi> of <hi>Church-Government, Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,</hi> the mother, and the daughter, the greater and the leſſe) to a juſtification from the Scripture, Scripture being made now adaies to ſpeake to every mans fancy: and thus whiles it was boaſted we had arrived in a Land of promiſe far remote from Romiſh, Popiſh, and Epiſcopall tyranny, and ſuperſtition, we were, as now we ſee, now our eyes are open, led back again as that Army of men was that came to beſiege <hi>Eliſha,</hi> brought as it were blindfold, and ſet downe in the midſt of <hi>Samaria;</hi> we find our ſelves in the midſt of Rome, Egypt, and Babylon; but as it now falls out, in the power and hands too, of thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, theſe Reformed Romaniſts had ſhut up, and beſieged, who are now (as many as are ſuch in truth) preparing food and neceſſaries for thoſe that would have been the ſlaughter of them.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Thus <hi>Aholah</hi> was no worſe then <hi>Aholibah,</hi> and <hi>Aholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116119:8"/> no better, but of the ſame complexion and adulterous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition with <hi>Aholah, Judah</hi> as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> as <hi>Judah,</hi> the Presbyters as the Biſhops, and the Biſhops as the Presbyters, and both as the Papiſts, for what was ſaid of the one, <hi>mutato nomine,</hi> might be ſaid of the other; hence it was they loved exceedingly, and longed to be together in one, as appeared by the Scots complying with the King, and that party as yet cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt: firſt at Oxford ſecretly, after at Newcaſtle, Holmby, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Hampton Court, Iſle of Wight openly; in all which they had the concurrence of the Engliſh Presbyter, who together like an imperious whoriſh woman, <hi>open their feet to their Lovers</hi> (whom they had courted before in private) upon every <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and hill,</hi> to the apparent view, and diſcerning of all; ſo that there is now a marriage made, or a reunion at leaſt, in heart and will betwixt the King and Parliament, Biſhops and Presbyters, (which the King obſerved well enough, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being at the Treaty asked by one of his friends, what he thought of M. <hi>Seaman</hi> and others, he anſwered him in the eare, yet ſo as others heard, why they would be Biſhops man) this union was not in <hi>God</hi> or in <hi>Christ,</hi> but in the common enemy of both <hi>Satan</hi> the <hi>Accuſer,</hi> and deſtroyer of all good in all, ſo that the Biſhops now lived in the Presbyters, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell Table, and other the high Commiſſion, and the Courts Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick, Monopoly-men in the Parliament and Synod, and their <hi>firſt borne,</hi> their ſeverall Committees, ſo that by this means, a bridge is made for one, to paſſe over to the other, plain and eaſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116119:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> 
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How this preſent Army appeared firſt in the light of God, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, in the darkneſſe of this world.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">§. 1. BUt Captaine, Army, or rather Mr. Agitator, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and ſince call'd Leveller ſteps in (as one late jeeringly writ) and forbids their actuall, outward and open coming together, ſeeing it ſo illegitimate, and tending ſo to the prejudiſe of all, even of the very parties themſelves; and to that end whiles the King longs, or rather luſts after the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Parliament after him; This bold, young, manly, and yet faire, and as yet untoucht Virgin, at leaſt ſo in her own account, and in a good meaſure ſo in truth, and certainly ſo in compariſon of others (thoſe adulterous women or people I have ſpoken of hitherto) I mean that honeſt principle and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in and out of the Army, theſe (I ſay) are ſo bold to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the King as though they meant a marriage with him, which they did not out of pure love, but to prevent his union with either of the two former, which they judged, as unfit for him, as he for them, and to that end poſſeſſe themſelves of his perſon, and ſo in him, or becauſe of him they take the greater boldneſſe, to ſeize upon the Parliament, whom the King liked better, as being more like him, in diſpoſition, and complexion; and this they did, having the ſword, the better end of the ſtaffe of power in their own hands, not firſt at leaſt appearingly, by the approvement, and ſome think ſcarce really at all, or at leaſt not till afterwards, and that rather out of neceſſity, then good will concur'd with, and aſſented unto, by many, if not almoſt all the heads of the Army; but for one end or another they are now all united as one man, having an evident, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt preſence of God upon them, they reſolve to be his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and ſervants for the Kingdomes good and peace, and to withſtand all without difference oppoſing it, ſeeking without reſpect of perſons, the profit and honeſt intereſt of all, the King, Queen and Cavaliers not excepted, as appeares in their Propoſalls, and therefore they make addreſſes to him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time more open, and ſometime more private, that upon his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116119:9"/> concurring with them, they would proſecute his juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full intereſt, as well as their owne, and upon this account they march to London to chaſtiſe the follies of the Parliament, and checke and put a ſtop to her unreaſonable luſtings after the King, and other the onions and garlick of Aegipt, as apt to breed evill diſeaſes in them, ſo that in this they were a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving to the King and thoſe of his ſide, who thought but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to attaine onely to the forbidden tree by them, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſatisfie their own luſts, which yet I will not altogether affirme, but this I do openly profeſſe, and declare, that this overture with the King, was the moſt hopefull, promiſing, innocent, candid, and Chriſtian, that ever was made ſince theſe troubles began, and the moſt like to bring forth the wiſhed for peace truth and righteouſneſſe, to and for the reſt of all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Nation, without reſpect of perſons; into which, unleſſe the door ſtand equally open unto all, it is like, nay it will certainly be ſhut againſt all, it being the nature of all good men and governments, to give downe like the Sun in the firmament, light &amp; warmth as well to the benefit and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the unjuſt and unrighteous, (though not for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, as ſuch, but for their conviction) as the juſt and righteous, according to the <hi>patterne</hi> given us in the <hi>Mount,</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt himſelfe,</hi> to whom the <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Harlots,</hi> which were outwardly unclean, as that party of people are, which we in our ſelfe juſtifying language, have and do call <hi>Malignants,</hi> had as eaſie and open acceſſe as the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> which were only outwardly holy and cleane, but within were full of <hi>rottenneſſe and filth,</hi> as the moſt of thoſe are, on the other ſide, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us that boaſt of their Saintſhip and reformation. This ſun of righteouſneſſe, mercy, and peace, was dawning in that day, I ſay an appearing of righteouſneſſe and peace: of Juſtice and mercy: for the one without the other is not in God, or Chriſt, or good men, and therefore where they are divided as for the moſt part they are brought forth among men, they are not in truth, but in pretence.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. And therefore I do utterly diſlike the late unreaſonable Jewiſh, Heatheniſh, unchriſtian outcry, or clamour for juſtice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116119:9"/> to be done upon the perſon of the King and thoſe of his party; and no mention made of <hi>mercy, love, grace, goodneſſe, reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> nor reaching forth the arms, and turning of the <hi>bowels of compaſſion</hi> towards him and them; it being certain, the former is not of God without the later; yea, the former without the later, doth but irritate, provoke, and ſtir up anger, wrath, war and tumults, to the confuſion of the Nation. And therefore I affirm again, That that overture with the King, as it was more Chriſtian, ſo it was infinitely more probable to bring in truth and peace, then is the preſent courſe taken, though by the ſame party and perſons.</p>
               <p n="3">SECT. 3. But an eclipſe came ſuddenly upon this Sun, that it ſet even at noon-day upon the whole kingdom, and all the Heads of it, King, Parliament, Army, Engliſh and Scots: The common Mother of the good and peace of all being forcibly made to withhold her <hi>breſts;</hi> her Son, the <hi>man-childe</hi> of all our hope, being taken up to God, and to his throne, ruling yet among men, though in a hidden and ſecret way: the woman her ſelf (thoſe weak and feeble people) being fain to fly into the <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> to hide her ſelf, not appearing ſcarce with any comelineſſe or beauty at all among men: <hi>ſhe hath a place prepared of God, where ſhee is nouriſhed for a time, times, and half a time, from the face of the Serpent:</hi> that is, (as <hi>Paraeus</hi> on the <hi>Revelation</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth well, a time ſeeming lon, but proving ſhort.</p>
               <p n="4">SECT. 4. And now, <hi>Behold, the Divel is come down again amongſt men, having great wrath,</hi> reigning, raging working, confounding, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Councels, of <hi>King, Lords, Commons, Biſhops, Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Levellers</hi> and all; In all whoſe counſels and projects appeared manifeſt weakneſſe, errour, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; yea, open wickedneſſe and Apoſtacy in ſome: The retiring himſelf for reſt, and recovery out of his loſt eſtate, into his old principles, and compliances with his Biſhops, and now again beginning to be revived party, who are prepared every one in ſecret to engage again, and to revive their old and almoſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116119:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116119:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116119:11"/> crucified Cauſe; which immediately after broke forth into a more fierce and cruel War, almoſt in all parts. That which nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and gave life again to this dying Cauſe, was apparantly, and to the view of all, the treble Apoſtacy of the Army it ſelf, <hi>England</hi>'s glory, that I ſay not, <hi>England</hi>'s pride. And I pray God that ſpirit that is too potent in them, which was both the life and ruine of both King and Parliament, prove not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion both their own and the kingdoms ruine. 1. This Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, this ſo Saint-like Army fell, firſt from making good thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Propoſals they had made in the behalf of the King; which gave too much cauſe to the King and his party to deſiſt from their expectation of ſalvation, and hope from them, which they had too, before-hand given them juſt cauſe to look for from them. 2. They fell from any further concurrence with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Agitators, which now they begin violently to oppoſe; that I ſay not, exaſperate, yea purſue and perſecute: witneſſe the ſtrife at <hi>Putney,</hi> the unrighteous and untrue ſuggeſtion that was made of them to the King, as though they intended to lay hands on him in ſecret, or indeed, at all: which oppoſition grew to that height and heat, that either ſide appeared in a way of open war againſt the other; folly in the one, begetting phrenſie and fury in the other: ſo that the Heads of the Army impriſoned their own perſons and errours, in the perſons and errours of others; ſo that they themſelves were not free, till they had repented, and ſet the other as free as themſelves. This awakened the Spirit of God in <hi>Sedgwick, Saltmarſh, Pinnell, Ingrave,</hi> like the Angel of God that met <hi>Balaam</hi> riding beyond his Commiſſion, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and profeſſedly to oppoſe and ſtand in their way: ſo that even as the dumb Aſſe reproved the madneſſe of the Prophet; ſo at the light of God appearing in theſe men, the very naturall ſtrength and ſinews of the Army ſtood ſenſleſs, as a brute ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed animal, not able to go either backward or forward; either back to a complyance with the honeſt principles of the Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or forward in their acquieſcing in the Parliaments Votes and Counſels. Which leads (3) to a diſcovery of the third de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of their deparure from their faith, hope, and firſt good purpoſe: to wit, their hiding and burying that good principle of ſeeking without partiality the good and freedom of all, like
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116119:11"/> the earth, our common parent, eſpecially the <hi>new Earth, Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, which is above,</hi> the true parent of all the Children that are truly and eternally free, in the freedom of God and <hi>Chriſt himſelf:</hi> I ſay, in ſtead of this, they bury this good and uſefull talent, or rather <hi>bottle it up</hi> in one ſort of Veſſels, whence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe that great ſtrife at <hi>Windſor</hi> about Ordinances, having this only, for the moſt part, like the Jewes to diſtinguiſh themſelves from the Gentiles; and for this cauſe manifeſtly oppoſing, that I ſay not brow-beating, and perſecuting thoſe that profeſſed to live in no other Ordinance, but that which is the ſame in all ages, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>following the Lamb whitherſoever he goes;</hi> whoſe words and lives are a continuall witneſſing to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by whom is pulled down in all ages the <hi>partition wall</hi> betwixt Iews and Gentiles, the <hi>ſtricter</hi> and looſer ſort of men, that equal acceſs may be for both to God, by him, they being all alike good, or alike bad before him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Confuſion or trouble that came upon the Army, and the whole Kingdom, upon the Eclipſe of this Sun.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1.</head>
                  <p>THus <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his light, truth and glory, is again <hi>crucified,</hi> that I ſay not dead and buried, even in the Army it ſelf; whence it followes that in this darke and gloomy day, ſuch is the ſtate of all things in the deniall of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the only <hi>life</hi> and <hi>light</hi> of <hi>man;</hi> I ſay in this dark day, or <hi>night</hi> rather, for in the abſence of the Sun the day is as the night, the wilde beaſts break forth again, and come abroad; firſt in Wales, having this Spirit form'd and moulded in them, by the like appearing in a great though not ſo great a degree, firſt in the Parliament, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great ſhaking of it, like the <hi>fig-tree,</hi> by the march of the Army to their door, by which ſome of thoſe many unripe and uſeleſs Figgs and fruit fell to the earth; and not only in them, but even in the Army it ſelf, profeſſing a better ſpirit, dealing with too much roughneſs, and occaſion of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116119:12"/> with thoſe <hi>quondam</hi>-Parliament Colonels, <hi>Laughorue, Poyer,</hi> and <hi>Powell,</hi> who not being led with good words, or good dealing, which they call good payment, out of their command, as they might have been, ſcorned; which yet was their pride and error, to be commanded out of all, and therefore put all upon the adventure, and have ſince for their folly loſt all, and are now priſoners, expecting the ſentence of Death upon ſome of them. Now though the Army, (the honeſt faithfull and victorious Army, for comparatively I have alwayes accounted it ſo,) were a ſcourge not only to them in <hi>Wales,</hi> but them too in <hi>Kent, Colchester,</hi> the great Army of <hi>Scots,</hi> that bubble of of an Army, (though they conſiſted, they ſay, of above two millions of men) headed there by Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and the like comparatively nearer at home, by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Holland;</hi> I ſay, though it be apparent that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was a ſcourge, and a ſharp one too, to theſe laſt and dying fainting re-onſets of thoſe, that would, but were not appointed of God to live and riſe again; and therefore ſtronger was he that fought againſt them, then he that engaged in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 2.</head>
                  <p>Yet it cannot be denied by any good Chriſtian, or any true principles of Chriſtianity, but that they alſo were a ſcourge, yea, a bitter and ſharp one too, diſcovering the evil of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to themſelves, awakening the good principles that lay bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in them; ſo that I may boldly ſay, They were the rod of God chaſtiſing them, there being I beleeve (to ſpeak the leaſt) many hundreds of them loſt their lives, and of them many an honeſt and good man. So that though the Army ſee many and grievous offences in thoſe given into their hands this Summer; yet certainly they have cauſe, if they look into themſelves, to complain of their own giving too much occaſion, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voluntarily; their own errors having too great an influence, like ſome malignant Stars, to engender the like errors in others, ſo that upon the matter, which I mention, that they might not boaſt either before God or men; and while they complain of others faults, they would remember their own, and be more faultleſs themſelves, before they be over-haſty and violent againſt the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116119:12"/> faults of Others;) I ſay, what have they done, but puniſhed their own errors upon the backs of others, though according to State-rules, they were greater offendors then themſelves.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The divers kinds of fruit brought forth this ſummer, like <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> figgs, <hi>ſome very</hi> bad, <hi>ſome very good:</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1.</head>
                  <p>THe fruit brought forth in this Summers engagement (which uſe to be either good, and ſo for the health of men; or bad, tending to the nouriſhment of evill humors and deſeaſes in the bodies and minds of men) was indeed like <hi>Jeremiah's figgs, ſome very good,</hi> even like the <hi>figgs</hi> that are firſt <hi>ripe,</hi> but the other very bad, that they cannot be eaten they were ſo naught; the bad were ſo naught, that there was little or no diſcerning of the good; the bad were of three ſorts, whereof the firſt was very pleaſant and deſirable in the eye of ſenſe, but very peſtilent to the heart and ſtomack: and this I call either firſt the underhand dealing of the Scots with the Engliſh, and the Engliſh with them, they both with the King, and the King with both, by which his perſon was wronged, and the evill principle too much nouriſhed in him, by its like in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Parliaments of both Kingdoms, who muſt needs be acceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry and ſo guilty of the evill, is ſo violently and without mixture of mercy charged alſo on him; the appearance of this fruit, being very pleaſant in the eyes of moſt, was deſired by moſt, and therefore the moſt and beſt were deceived into the liking of it, and have ſince found it to be of an evill nature, ſo that this was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther door opened to the corrupt principle of the King to come out at, and manifeſt it ſelf to his prejudice; for had he not been thus complyed with, firſt by the Army, ſince by the Parliament, and Scots, it might (through the manifold afflictions that have been upon him, with the bleſſing, grace and mercy of God, which is alwayes open to him) have been more apparently mortified in him, ſo that heer it again appears the King's fault may be devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on thoſe that ſtrenthned it in him, aſwell as charged on him alone, they being no more righteous then he.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116119:13"/>
                  <head>SECT. 2.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond ſort of bad and evill fruit, I call all thoſe periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hopes of all thoſe appeared again in A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes this ſummer, They having been both <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> like the multitude the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.7 8. that fought againſt <hi>Ariell</hi> that is the <hi>Lion of God,</hi> which is as much to ſay as the <hi>Iſrael</hi> or Church of God, <hi>for the remnant of Jacob ſhall be among the Nations in the midst of many people, a as Lion among the beaſts of the forreſt, as a young Lion among the flocks of ſheep, who if he go</hi> through, both <hi>treadeth down</hi> and <hi>teareth</hi> in <hi>peeces,</hi> and <hi>none can deliver.</hi> I ſay, all the Armie and engagements this ſummer that have come up againſt the <hi>Lion of the tribe of Judah,</hi> this <hi>Ariell</hi> the Church in Chriſt, Chriſt in the Church, they all hath been <hi>as a dream of a night viſion,</hi> that they have ſeen, <hi>as when an hungry man dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> and <hi>behold he eateth,</hi> but he <hi>awaketh</hi> and his <hi>ſoul is empty,</hi> or when a <hi>thirſty man dreameth,</hi> and <hi>behold he drinketh, but he awaketh</hi> as they have done at their ſcattering, routing, ſlaying, killing, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, and his ſoul hath appetite, ſo ſhall the multitude of all the Nations be that fight againſt <hi>Mount-Sion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 3.</head>
                  <p>The other part of the bitter fruit of which I ſpeak, The Army and Kingdom have been fain though ſore againſt their will and deſire to taſte, and that hath been their many fears, troubles, affrights, plunders, ruines, wounds, death, and loſſe which they have been fain to pertake of, as the fruits of their own, aſwell as others errours; but God who is able &amp; ſometimes wont of theſe and ſuch ſtones to make bread, gave many of them bread to eate, which others as they would not, ſo they knew not of; and this I call the good fruit, which the Army themſelves, and the Nation by them, have given them to feed upon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 4.</head>
                  <p>And this doth appear thus, in that they have not only with <hi>Samſon</hi> been delivered together with the whole Nation, out of the paw and power of the ramping and roaring Lion, the Army in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116119:13"/> the field, and the young Lion, the Lion in the Lambs skin, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in policy, and undermining at home: nor onely in that they have had power over both theſe Lions, <hi>rending them</hi> as he did, even as they would have <hi>rent a kid;</hi> but that alſo in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe of both is found a <hi>ſwarm of Bees,</hi> a ſort of men gathering, feeding on, and yet yeelding honey to others: which though a riddle, hath appeared true in part; but that there be two ſorts of Bees among them; which, for diſtinction ſake, I will for the preſent call, after the language of thoſe that converſe with thoſe kinde of cattell, the one is profitable, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther unprofitable; the laſt is the humming Bee, the drone, or lazy Bee.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A deſcription of the corrupt and excrementitious, together with the good and uſefull part of the Army.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1.</head>
                  <p>IN the firſt ſort I finde theſe three properties: The firſt is, they make as great a buzzing and noyſe about and for <hi>Juſtice, Peace, Righteouſneſſe, Religion, Liberty, Equity, Saintſhip;</hi> and on the other ſide, againſt Tyranny, Oppreſſion, Superſtition, &amp;c. nay, a far greater then any of the reſt; becauſe having far leſſe then others, he is neceſſitated to make the greater ſhew of zeal for the one, and againſt the other; when in mean time he is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ignorant of, yea altogether an enemy to, and in ſecret, yea in his life oppoſing of the firſt where-ever it doth appear; and on the other ſide, one that hath no other principle but that which feeds, and gives life and being to all the evill in the Land.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 2.</head>
                  <p>Another property of this kinde of cattel, is, the purſuit of that which is alone as honey to them; that is, their own profit, honour, eaſe, wealth: and they may eaſily be diſcerned from others, as excelling all others in <hi>pride, vanity, folly, ſuperciliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, overlooking, ov rtopping</hi> the <hi>honeſt, quiet, meek,</hi> and <hi>ſilent ſpirited men</hi> among them. As for theſe, if they would have ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116119:14"/> it is for themſelves; if liberty, it is for their luſts: Theſe are like thoſe flies, that infeſt thoſe ſores of the already galled, grieved ſpirit of the Land; that are ſo far from healing, that they keep the wounds of it raw and open, and are indeed to the good ſpirit of God in the Army, as <hi>Peter</hi> was in his pride and ignorance to Chriſt, even as Satan himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 3.</head>
                  <p>I will name but one property more of theſe unprofitable men, and that is this, They detain and keep others from the <hi>hive,</hi> and the <hi>taſte</hi> of the honey-comb; being indeed a veile, or a hedge of briers and thorns, impriſoning, concealing, clouding the <hi>Son</hi> of righteouſneſe, which is behinde this <hi>wall,</hi> within this <hi>hedge,</hi> on the other ſide this <hi>cloud;</hi> indeed the very <hi>Man of ſin</hi> and ſon of perdition, which muſt be taken out of the way before the <hi>Son of God</hi> will in his full <hi>light, ſweetn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> appear, to the healing of the Land, and they in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 4.</head>
                  <p>This is the firſt and worſt ſort of Bees, the excrementitious and unprofitable part of the Army, and thoſe that adhere to them. The other, which I onely prize as the good and uſefull ſort of Bees, ſuch as are more ſilent, more painfull, more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, of a leſſer ſize, in appearance, then the former, not ſo ſightly:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>At feſſae multa referunt ſe nocte minores</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Crura thymo plena.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>The leſſe and tyred Bees return at night,</l>
                           <l>Get much, but yeeld the fruits of all their might.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> Theſe are the <hi>light, life, reſt, peace, joy, hope,</hi> and <hi>healing</hi> of the Land; <hi>trees of righteouſneſſe</hi> (in the Lord) that bring forth fruit <hi>in ſeaſon,</hi> the very <hi>tree of life</hi> (in Chriſt) is appointed of God, and expected of men for the healing of the Nation, <hi>plant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of Gods <hi>own planting, Aaron</hi>'s <hi>rod,</hi> that at the ſame time <hi>buds, bloſſoms,</hi> and <hi>bears</hi> and yeelds <hi>Almonds;</hi> the <hi>rod of Moſes,</hi> by which he did all thoſe wonders in <hi>Egypt,</hi> devoured the rods of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> gave
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116119:14"/> them no reſt till they were <hi>made free:</hi> In one word, the very <hi>rod of God,</hi> the ſcepter of his right hand, by which he divided the <hi>red ſea,</hi> and by which he overturned the Nations that ſtand in his way of <hi>love to them,</hi> that he <hi>who bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th himſelf in the earth, may bleſſe himſelf in the God of truth.</hi> If any reſt or recovering be brought to King, Parliament, and all others in the Land, it muſt be by them, for the annoynting of God is upon them, and them alone to that end.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A comparing the Armies former pretences, with their preſent act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings together.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1.</head>
                  <p>THis Sun hath not appeared, no not in this laſt engagement, in that beauty, brightneſs and ſplendor it did the firſt time they aſſayed the ſame thing: In this they are more ſevere, rigid, fierce, unmercifull toward the King, and thoſe in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with him, then they were before; and therefore appear more Jewiſh, heatheniſh, fearfull, diſobedient to God, and unbelieving, all which tend to the hardening of their hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and them. Firſt againſt God; for I may ſay it bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the name of God, call'd upon by the Army, is blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe Gentiles (for ſo they are in account by moſt) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Army, in that the fruits of that Spirit, the true an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting they pretend to, appears not, except in word, to all. Secondly, As their heart is hardened againſt God, ſo againſt them; for they can finde no place of reſt, love, or mercy in them, that they might be called and provoked to lie down in their boſoms as on their bed of reſt: but contrariwiſe, when they think of them or ſee them, they are fraught with fear, trouble, wrath, and emnity againſt them, becauſe they look for the like meaſure from them. Whereas, if love, mercy, forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and compaſſion did appear in the Army, and others to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch, it would transform them into the ſame image, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116119:15"/> melt them into the love and knowledge of God: after this manner God perſwades <hi>Jophet</hi> to dwell in the tents of <hi>Shem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 2.</head>
                  <p>The evill then of the King and Parliament is oppoſed either by the good or evill of the Army. The evill of the Army, though it doth and may oppoſe the evill of both, though not as evill: the luſts leading and reigning in the Army may be brought forth in a way of zeal for juſtice, and under a pretence of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, peace, truth, liberty, to oppoſe luſts of another name and cogniſance in the King and Parliament; this conteſt is but like <hi>Satan</hi>'s going about to <hi>caſt out Satan,</hi> whereby <hi>his kingdom</hi> is no wayes weakened, but confirmed, evill in the Army nouriſheth and promotes evill in the King; <hi>wrath, malice, revenge</hi> in the <hi>one,</hi> maintains and upholds it in the <hi>other.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 3.</head>
                  <p>This then is the iron <hi>gate</hi> and door of braſſe and ſteel that ſhuts righteouſneſs, truth, peace and love out from the view, peace and reſt of men in them: by this the King and Biſhops ruled, and by this they were ruined too: The ſame courſe took the Parliament, and were brought into the ſame Labyrinth as was the King. And ſo far as the Armie walks by this rule, they run the ſame hazard, will ſplit themſelves upon the ſame rock yea, are for the preſent, in reſpect of that principle, in the ſame <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ander,</hi> in the ſame pit, where is no water but that which moiſtens, faſtens, fattens that evill root and bitter in them, whence comes forth nothing but weeds, briers and brambles, the fruit of the firſt earth, which is under the curſe, and is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally to paſſe away, whereby they are a vexation and torment, yea, divels to themſelves and all ſorts of men in the Land.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 4.</head>
                  <p>That then that is worthy of applauſe in the Army in their preſent undertakings, is their good, or rather the goodneſſe of God in them, oppoſing the evill, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the evill One in King and Parliament: This alone
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116119:15"/> is to be reckoned among the Saint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (as we hope they are) as the common enemy of the Land; this is onely worthy of all oppoſition: let this be withſtood to death and bonds. It's a great miſtake, and by all means to be removed out of the hearts and mindes of men, that the ſword of ſteel, or the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of war have gotten them ſucceſſe and victory over the other ſide; nay, it hath been the word of the Lord, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and preſence of God, helping the one, and oppoſing the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thou <hi>haſt loved righteouſneſſe, and hated iniquity:</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>Annointing</hi> in the <hi>Church) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, even thy God hath annointed thee with the oyl of gladneſſe above thy fellows;</hi> that is, thou getſt the better <hi>upon this account,</hi> and art too hard for all other Companies, and Armies of men whatſoever, becauſe of this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the door of hope was opened to the King, and is to his party in the valley of Achor, or forlorne state of trouble they are in.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> TO conclude: The caſe then of the King, Parliament, Army, and all eſtates of men in the Nation, was &amp; is this: 1. Of the King; he had the Kingdom, and in it all that was comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all the glory, fulneſſe, beauty and riches in it, the head and foot, himſelf, his Queen, his Crown, his Children, his great Eſtate, Attendance, Honour, Glory, People, &amp;c. But all this in the fleſh, in and after, or according to the <hi>old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitfull luſts,</hi> which like an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> led him and all of the ſame ſpirit with him, <hi>huc &amp; illuc,</hi> after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall objects of reſt and delight, all which yet <hi>periſhed in the uſe;</hi> it being, in reſpect of his way of enjoying of it, <hi>but as the graſſe of the field, or corn upon the houſe top, which withereth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be grown up:</hi> nothing is in it but that which is <hi>earthly, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall</hi> and <hi>diveliſh;</hi> all appearances are of a like nature; but not of one and the ſame form, all from beneath, ſome black, and ſome white Divels: his fearing one, and following the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116119:16"/> hath not ſuffered him to enjoy any laſting reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> The Almighty then hath by the loſſe of all the Kings glory, greatneſs, his Queen, his Servants; yea, and ſince, his naturall and bodily life, ſhut him up ſo, that he hath had no liberty in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed enjoyments, as to the outward, fleſhly, or ſenſuall man: this was therefore to the King in reſpect of the old man, <hi>the valley of Achor,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>valley of trouble:</hi> but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Perſon, and Gods intendment, yea, and the longing prayer and endeavour of all good men, in whom is the ſure and laſting mercies of God, and the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt, it was to him, and 'tis to all his friends, and thoſe that took part with him, for a <hi>door of hope.</hi> In this <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> of trouble in reſpect of the outward man, God returns (which thing I will not deny) and gives in again into the heart of the King, together with himſelf,<note n="*" place="margin">For the fulneſs of all things is in God in Chriſt.</note> all things, his Crown, his Queen, his Kingdom, &amp;c. but waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and made white, that he might enjoy them eternally and without interruption in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> And to this, he was, and thoſe they call the Royalliſts are in a greater propinquity, and more likelihood to attain unto, then many either of the Parliament or Army; who are like <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum,</hi> lifted up in a glorious fig-leave profeſſion as <hi>high as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> their turn will be next to be hurled down to hell, the hell in which the King was, whiles many of that ſide (the by-word, eſpecially of the profeſſing people) ſhall be lifted up to <hi>heaven, and made to ſit with God in Chriſt in heavenly places; for there ſhall come from Eaſt and West, and places</hi> and conditions moſt remote, and ſhall ſit with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob in the Kingdom of God,</hi> and the ſuppoſed <hi>children of the kingdom cast out:</hi> For <hi>God will not</hi> (though it may be, man would) <hi>contend for ever;</hi> neither <hi>will I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be alwayes wroth, for the ſpirit ſhould fail before me, and the ſouls which I have made. For the iniquity of his covetouſneſſe was I wroth, and ſmote him; I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on frowardly in the way of his heart: I have ſeen his wayes, and will heal him, I will lead him alſo, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore comforts to him and his mourners.</hi> For the language of Chriſt is to this day in the Church, ſpeaking as 'tis written, <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord God is upon me, becauſe the Lord hath annointed me to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116119:16"/> preach good tidings to the meek; he hath ſent me to bind up the broken hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives and the opening of the priſon doors to them that are bound.</hi> This I profeſſe my ſelf to be daily in expectation of, according as it is written, <hi>The firſt ſhall be laſt and the laſt firſt:</hi> the Jews, and thoſe that profeſſe the knowledge of God after the letter, ſhall be provoked, and made aſhamed by a fooliſh and deſpiſed people: the Gentiles, which make no ſuch profeſſion, ſhall be before-hand with them in the knowledge of God and Chriſt, in ſpirit, power and truth: To which I ſay and pray, <hi>Deus faxit,</hi> This thing, O God, bring to paſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the glory of the Parliament at their firſt aſſembling together, with the cauſe of their ruine; <hi>viz.</hi> their dividing themſelves into a threefold Schiſm, Royaliſts, Preſbyters, Independent; with the hurtfull principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of each.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> THe ſecond is the ſtate and condition of the old, and now decayed and worn out Parliament: together with the ſtate of all them that ſhrouded themſelves under the ſhadow of this great and tall, but now fallen Cedar. This people had their day <hi>(.i.)</hi> their morning, noon, and evening-tide. Whiles 'twas yet morning, or young dayes with them, they began (according to the Country Proverb) as a new broom, to ſweep all clean: and therefore made themſelves, after the ſimilitude of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (the true pattern of all good and wholſome undertakements) a <hi>new threſhing inst<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ument having teeth,</hi> that with it they <hi>might threſh the mountains</hi> of Pride, Superſtition, Oppreſſion; they made them a <hi>ſcourge of ſmall cords,</hi> and minded indeed to cleanſe the Temple, and to caſt out the buyers and ſellers of <hi>doves,</hi> thoſe more innocent and harmleſſe ones in the Land, of whom theſe money-changers made merchandize, (as 'tis ſaid) <hi>They ſhall make Merchandize of you:</hi> For they did, as Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> caſt out
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116119:17"/> the gain gotten by doves. In one word, their going forth was like the morning Sun, rejoycing <hi>as a Giant</hi> (newly awoke out of ſleep, and ſilence in the Land) <hi>to run his courſe</hi> of light and truth: ſo that by them, as by the Womans ſeed, (Chriſt born in ſpirit and power among them) the Serpents head (that is to ſay) the wit, power, policy, enmity that prevailed in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Hierarchy, Monarchy (for the laſt was above the firſt) was wonderfully diſcovered, bruiſed, ſpoiled and diſappointed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> And therefore this Serpent after a while betook himſelf to another courſe, ſought after another and more ſecure place to ſave and hide his head; ſo that whiles <hi>theſe huſbandmen ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pt,</hi> though before-hand the Lord of the harveſt had ſowed <hi>good ſeed</hi> among them, the <hi>enemy</hi> came in by <hi>night,</hi> the night of their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and <hi>ſowed tares;</hi> that this garden of God, that at firſt ſeemed an earthly Paradiſe, was full fraught with weeds, I mean, pride, ignorance of God, ſelf-ſeeking, faction, not going oc together in bearing the burthen of the Kingdom (as at firſt) with one ſhoulder; but as <hi>untamed heifers,</hi> according to the Scripture phraſe, <hi>unaccustomed to the yoak</hi> of Chriſt, (that is to ſay, his preſence and government in truth, peace, mercy, juſtice, <hi>his ſeat and throne</hi>) they all hung back, or drew contrary ways one to another: ſo that while every party and faction minded their own particular ſafety, honour, greatneſſe, the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was neglected, and that ſtool of reſt intended and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by them, and from them, being removed out of the way by their own party-making; the whole wearied body of the Kingdom did begin again to fall quite to the ground. This was the <hi>forbidden fruit</hi> that the whole Parliament in their ſeverall parties were overtaken with: for if the <hi>Paradiſe of God</hi> were not ſecure, but that the Serpent got in there to deceive the woman, no marvel he had admiſſion here, where there was ſo much of the woman (weakneſs and inability to overcome temptation, and diſcern the hour of it) that they <hi>all ſought their own things, and few or none the things of Jeſus Christ.</hi> which might make for the reſt and profit of the whole.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> And to that end, having ſeverall forms and patterns in their mindes, of ways and methods to make a <hi>bed of rest</hi> to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116119:17"/> they all proved <hi>too narrow,</hi> or <hi>too ſhort;</hi> ſo that there was not room in't for all: for that which would firſt ſerve the turn of the Royall party, was too noyſome and offenſive, as a defiled and polluted bed, a bed of whoredom and luſt; and therefore theſe were as a ſmoke to the noſe of the pre-ingaged, or fore-reſolved men of the Presbyterian or Scotiſh way, who proclaim with open mouth the <hi>jus Divinum</hi> of their own new invention; and therefore preach, and print, and hold out to the world at at home and abroad, as though Chriſt had ſaid to them and that order of men, what he did, and alwayes doth to his true and onely Spouſe (which is alwayes hid with him in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not at all expoſed to common view; for as Chriſt, ſo is the Church (as in union with him, or as his Spouſe) hid to the world) <hi>Behold, thou art fair, my Love, behold, thou art fair, (yea, our bed</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is green</hi>) and the onely flouriſhing, fruitfull, hopefull woman or Church in the world. Yet this alſo takes after her <hi>ſiſter,</hi> and juſtifies them that had gone before, in all their abominations, and all her children prove <hi>the ſons of the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſſe, and the whore,</hi> neither had any of them a heart to plead (in the behalf of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi>) againſt their <hi>Mother,</hi> making it appear, <hi>ſhe was not his Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> This Woman, or <hi>prevailing</hi> party in Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, uſurps all power, and takes all authority into their own hand, and boaſts, ſhe is Lady and Queen of Great Britain, at leaſt; therefore makes uſe of it to the eſtabliſhing of her ſelf, and depreſſing of all others, that would not, or could not ſing her ſong, drink of her cup, or dance after her pipe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore makes a decree, that none ſhould <hi>either buy or ſell,</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not her <hi>mark in their hand or forehead.</hi> But whiles ſhe is thus <hi>drunk, but not with wine,</hi> and thinks <hi>ſhe is,</hi> and none beſides her, even in that <hi>very hour,</hi> it is ſaid to her, as to her mother before, out of whoſe womb ſhe ſprang, <hi>Babylon the great, How much ſhe hath glorified her ſelf, and lived deliciouſly, ſo much tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſorrow give her. Therefore her plagues come in one day,</hi> (while it was yet noon-tide with this new invented Idol) <hi>death, mourning, and famine</hi> (of all that power, wiſdom, policy, and great riches that did ſuſtain her) and ſhe ſhall, as her elder
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116119:18"/> ſiſter <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Samariah</hi> the Popiſh and Epiſcopal Church, be utterly burnt with fire; <hi>for ſtrong is the Lord God in the Church,</hi> that hath undertaken to <hi>judge her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>5</label> And now behold all <hi>her Princes,</hi> and thoſe that reigned as Kings by means of her; yea, all the <hi>Merchants</hi> of this ſeeming new, but indeed the <hi>firſt earth</hi> that was to paſſe away, that had enriched themſelves by her ſorceries and whoredoms, that were as ſo many bawds and Panders to this Adulterous woman, are <hi>now ſtanding afar off, weeping,</hi> and making great lamentation, foraſmuch as <hi>no man buyeth of their merchandiſe any more,</hi> for <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her ſmoke goeth up for ever and ever.</hi> Thus now the pit theſe dug for other, they are faln into themſelves; ſo that it may be ſaid to them, by thoſe that were in the pit before them, as it was by thoſe that were in the like caſe to <hi>Babylon</hi> and the King thereof, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.10. when he came into the like condition with them <hi>Art thou alſo become weak as we are? art thou become like unto us? thy pomp is brought down to the grave, and the noiſe of thy viols is ceaſed: the worm Jacob is ſpread under thee, and the worms</hi> (ſuch as thou haſt deſpiſed) <hi>cover thee,</hi> that thou haſt no glory left. Thus this party (and being but a party, and for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) ſeeking the poſſeſſion of all, loſt all, <hi>the bed of rest</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by them proving too ſhort, not onely for others, but themſelves; ſo that they are now as well as others, <hi>caſt out, to the loathing of their perſon,</hi> and ſhaking of the head of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, the very by-word of the people, and ſo caſt into the furnace, out of which many of them may come forth, pure and refined gold; which I beſeech God to grant and bring to paſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> The third part this City (the old Parliament) was broken and fallen into, would be Independent, at leaſt in reſpect of the two former; and therefore, though they would not come into the bed of reſt, made ready, or at leaſt preparing, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the other two, as proteſting againſt the defilement of both; yet many of them had in their hearts, according to their pattern in <hi>New England</hi> (though it was not policy for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to profeſſe it) to make themſelves the onely <hi>Sarah</hi> or <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris,</hi> and to caſt out al others as <hi>Agar,</hi> and not at all as the Wife
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116119:18"/> and Spouſe of God; yea, in effect, they openly declare it, though afterwards they ſaw a neceſſity of being of another minde; for they look'd upon the Presbyterian Church as an adulterous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and were loth to have any ſociety with her, or almoſt any of her Aſſemblies, as accounting them not in a capacity to be communicated with. Yet in many, their oppoſition againſt them was but to break open a way whereby the Serpents head in them might have more certain hope of reſt then in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, being now much more transformed into an Angel of light then before. And therefore, leſt the tail of Anabaptiſts and Sectaries (ſo in their own account) ſhould prejudice their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with their elder ſiſter, they, to pleaſe and ſooth the one, openly and before the Sun diſavowed the other in their Apologeticall Narration. Theſe neither being but a party, and moſtly for themſelves, were rather the vexation of the former, then the expectation of the meek and quiet in the Land, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive reſt and freedom by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>7</label> Thus we ſee of all the children the Kingdom hath yet brought forth, whether Royall and Epiſcopall Parliamentary Presbyters, or Independents as ſuch, none have been able to take her by the hand, as <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> to lead her into the land of expected reſt and freedom; they all (though Engliſh men) going into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts (as ſometimes King <hi>Ahaz</hi> did) to take the pattern of the Altar they intended to worſhip God by. The Royalliſts ſeek for, as being enamoured with, the old and new Hierarchy of Rome and England. The Presbyterians were no leſſe taken with that of Scotland. And the Jndependents, as much as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with that of Holland and New-England: So that no ſide having ſeen the pattern in the Mount (which is Chriſt in the ſpirit) as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, they all not knowing what was become of him (ſince aſcended) make together a murmuring in the camp, or chief Aſſembly in our Engliſh Iſrael, the Parliament, crying out to their ſeverall Aaronical Prieſts among them, <hi>Come, mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us gods to go before us; for as for this</hi> Moſes (Chriſt ſince aſcended upon high) <hi>we know not what is become of him.</hi> But he is now come upon them as a <hi>thief in the night</hi> of their blinde zeal and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and there ſhall not a man of them eſcape the ſword of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116119:19"/> juſtice. So that there is none of the old Parliament, as ſuch, whether Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, or Independent, but as they have all drank of, and been drunk, with Babylons golden cup; ſo they have, and do, and will yet more taſte of her plagues; yea, their torment ſhall be to be tormented day and night in the preſence of the holy <hi>Angels,</hi> that are ſent in truth from God, and in the <hi>preſence of the Lamb,</hi> the meek King, of the holy, meek, and quiet in the Land. The light that ſhines now in the evening of the late Parliamentary glory; ſo that in this dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe there ſhines forth this light unto them, to lead them forth of the <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> they are in, to the <hi>Land flowing with milk and honey:</hi> that is to ſay, the true <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> where is the <hi>Lamb, and all thoſe with his Fathers name on their fore-heads, harping with their harps,</hi> and ſinging that new ſong which none but thoſe that are redeemed from among men could <hi>learn;</hi> even thoſe, and onely thoſe in whoſe mouth there is found no guile; for <hi>they are without fault before the throne of God:</hi> To this reſt ſhew them O Lord the way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Where, of the Armie<hi>'s</hi> hopefull, but difficult riſe: their ſucceſſefull vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious progreſſe, the cloud of reproach they lay and acted under, their breaking forth in open light and glory, their ſinking again into the Earth, their riſing again, with cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, reprehenſions, directions given them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> IN the laſt place I ſhall ſet down the ſtate of the top power of the Nation, as it is for the time preſent; I mean, the Army: for a power above them there is not viſible in the Land. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, I ſhall obſerve firſt, the day of their ſmall, mean, and low beginning, and how they came to this height of power and regiment over the whole Land.</p>
               <p>The Parliament, in all their former power, policy, Armies, grew weak, and withered as a dry tree, and were indeed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of good, like the dry parched ground: yet becauſe God had not forgotten to be gracious, or left off his merci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116119:19"/> were of old: he cauſeth the <hi>earth to bring forth truth, whiles righteouſneſſe looks down from heaven:</hi> both which meeting and kiſſing each other in a company of honeſt and plain-hearted Chriſtian men, many of them having much of the true <hi>annoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon them, they are modelled, by a divine hand, into another new and diſtinct Army from all the reſt, and are indeed (as it is ſaid of the <hi>Branch of righteouſneſſe</hi>) men <hi>wondred at</hi> by all; yea, feared and ſuſpected as well of friends as foes; not onely their enemies abroad, but even their very friends and fautors at home; inſomuch, that this <hi>Hercules</hi> was very like to have been ſtrangled in the womb or cradle, at their very firſt ſetting forth and contriving; but that there was of the ſeed and ſtrength of God among them, that there could be no divination againſt them, nor inchantment againſt this new ſupplanter, for <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cob</hi> is their name. Theſe (come forth into an Army) paſſe thorow the Land from one end to the other, like <hi>Leviathan in the ſea,</hi> in the might of God, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aking</hi> (as it were) in the great waters <hi>their pastime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> ſo that all engagements againſt them prove as ſucceſleſs as doth mans endevours to draw out that great <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than out</hi> of the great deep. <hi>Canſt thou fill his skin with barbed irons, or his head with fiſh-spears: lay thy hand upon him, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the battell, and do ſo no more, behold, the hope of him is in vain. Shall not one be caſt down at his ſight of him: None is ſo fierce that dare ſtir him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> A great while this Arm of God, or rather, the <hi>lighting down of his Arm</hi> upon the Royall party appeared hid or vailed under the preſent and yet remaining Parliament power, which like the interpoſition of the earth betwixt the body of the Sun and us, darkned or kept in continuall ecclipſe, either thorow neglect or reproach, the new-born hope of the Nation, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; for ſo they were, both in reſpect of cruſhing that power of which all ſtood in fear, as alſo that they were the onely <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylum,</hi> or City of refuge to all the afflicted and oppreſſed people of the Nation. Here they centered, as in the preſence of God among them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> But at length they caſt off the yoak, and appear free (heirs of all things) independent, in reſpect of all power, but God
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116119:20"/> alone above them: and that firſt in their firſt, but ineffectuall March up to <hi>London:</hi> wherein it did befall them as it did <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, Gen.</hi> 38.27. for they had, as ſhe, twins in one womb; for behold, while they travelled and laboured to bring forth, one put forth his hand; that is to ſay, there was a weak appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thoſe principles and purpoſes of peace, truth, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs (ſince brought forth to greater perfection:) but they that undertook the midwifery of this ſo hopeful new-born babe, took immediately a ſcarlet, bloudy, perſecuting thred and tied about the finger of it at its firſt putting forth, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which onely this might be ſaid, <hi>This came forth firſt.</hi> When alſo it came to paſſe, that as this appearance drew back again into the womb (where it hath for a while been hid) that his <hi>brother</hi> or next neighbour (for evil is always nigh to good, but never one with it) got then the upper hand, and came forth firſt; for which cauſe it was and might be called<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Perru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptor.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeus.</note> 
                  <hi>Pharez,</hi> that is to ſay, A breach, or a Maker of a breach. Therefore it was ſaid by all that undertook the Midwifery of their firſt born to this later unexpected and undeſired brat, How haſt thou broken forth? this breach be upon thee; bear thou the burthen of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front done to thine elder brother, Truth and Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> This was the firſt appearance or defilement upon the Army; in this thing was their virginity (in which they had lived all the dayes of their affliction and trouble) firſt of all ſtained and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowred, whiles (like <hi>Dinah</hi>) they were not content to keep at home with God in the houſe of their Father <hi>Jacob,</hi> (who was and is a <hi>ſupplanter</hi> of none but his elder and worſer bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau,</hi> a man that lives upon the ſpoil of other) but [they] would be going abroad to ſee the daughters of the Land, and the faſhions of other people, which proved a ſnare unto them, and was indeed a reproach to their fathers houſe, making his name to ſtink among the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label> In this defiled eſtate, even (as I may ſo ſpeak) whiles they were <hi>ſore,</hi> and this great infirmity upon them, of their confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to, and (as it were) proſtituting of themſelves to <hi>Sechem</hi> and <hi>Hamor,</hi> promiſing to acquieſce the one in the other, all (King, Parliament, Army) being (as it were) circumciſed, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116119:20"/> of one Religion, there comes upon them <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> in the anger of God, the Engliſh and Scotiſh Forces (yet bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in their agreed upon Covenant:) <hi>Inſtruments of cruelty are in their habitations. O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecret, unto their Aſſembly mine honour be not thou united; for in their anger they ſlew a man, and in their ſelf-will they digged down a wall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> they both together firſt made, and then avenged the ſeeming holy, but corrupt league was made up between them: <hi>Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath, for it was cruel.</hi> After this great ſlaughter and captivity of men, God will (I hope) ſay of them as <hi>Jacob</hi> did of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi, I will divide them in Jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael, reſtore</hi> and <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie</hi> them among their brethren that abode in the Covenant and light of God. For though both ſides excuſe the matter (as they did) and ſay, Should our Siſter be dealt with as with an harlot? For the Royall party being now one with the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, and the Presbyterian one with them, they ſaid, Shall this holy Cauſe we have undertaken to defend by Covenant, be proſtitute to theſe uncircumciſed Independents and Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? Therefore they both openly and ſecretly prepare war againſt them, even whileſt they pretended to lean upon them. On the other ſide, the <hi>Army,</hi> (who indeed had the better end of the ſtaffe, and moſt cauſe of complaint: for though weakly, yet it may be for the moſt part honeſtly, run into their forenamed errour) alſo have their mouthes opened, and their hearts awakened, to ſee the diſhonour would come by dealing with <hi>Dinah</hi> as with an harlot, ſuffer that <hi>honeſt cauſe</hi> they had engaged in, and taken up their ſwords for, to be proſtituded to the luſts and wils of evil men (though themſelves had too too much betrayed it a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) promiſed to acquieſce in that Power which they knew in heart did not adhere unto them (for though they had their hands, yet they had not the hearts of moſt of them); yet in effect, and interpretatively in this laſt Summers War they made null their promiſe to acquieſce in the Parliament: but ſince they have done it openly and declaredly, as it appears in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance and proceedings.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>6</label> Now though theſe things afford no good ſavour in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116119:21"/> of thoſe, either at home or abroad, <hi>that by reaſon of uſe have their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern betwixt good and evill;</hi> and therefore the true <hi>Jacob</hi> in the midſt of them is making his complaints of both, though not of both in the like degree. This being the time of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s trouble, and <hi>Tamar</hi>'s travel, there comes forth now in the late tranſactions<note n="*" place="margin">Oriens, <hi>vel</hi> Ortum.</note> 
                  <hi>Zarah,</hi> that is to ſay, that which ſhould have come forth firſt, but was ſtrangled in the womb and crucified in the birth, but recovers life again, and appears now to be of right the firſt-born, to whom the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance doth belong; <hi>he that ſhould come,</hi> and wee are not to <hi>look for another:</hi> the good and holy One in the Army, and ſo in the Nation, ſeems for the preſent to be predominant, and Lord of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>7</label> But <hi>Rebeccah Jacob</hi>'s mother (the good people of the Land, whether the Remainder of the Parliament, or thoſe bearing office in the Army, and the honeſt men of the City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that have an influence into this engagement) making more haſte then good ſpeed, out of a good minde notwithſtanding, remembring the word and promiſe of God concerning <hi>Jacob, That the elder ſhould ſerve the younger,</hi> that <hi>Jacob,</hi> a plain-deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>ſmooth</hi> and honeſt man or men, ſhould have the <hi>bleſſing,</hi> the upper hand of <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſhe makes uſe rather of her policy then the promiſe of God, ſhe puts <hi>Jacob</hi> into the clothing or goodly rayment of this elder brother <hi>Eſau;</hi> which will no more fit or become him, then <hi>Sauls Armour</hi> did <hi>David,</hi> who was fain to put it of again when he had done, and betake himſelf alone to his <hi>ſling</hi> and <hi>ſtone</hi> to throw down the great <hi>Goliah,</hi> the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible means of the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>power of God,</hi> againſt which there neither is nor can be any prevailing. Whiles <hi>Jacob,</hi> this new and hopefull <hi>Supplanter</hi> of evill ſtands thus ready to adminiſter <hi>ſavoury meat</hi> to the dying kingdom, as he did to his father <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> which now in his old age could ſcarce diſcern one thing from another; yet coming neer and feeling whether this be his very ſon <hi>Eſau</hi> (which is beſt beloved of his father, and moſt deſired of the Nation) or no: findes and concludes as he did, The voice is <hi>Jacobs voice, but the hands are the hands of</hi> Eſau: this deceit of this good woman, and this good mans complying
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116119:21"/> with her therein, coſt her much ſorrow and grief, being fain after a while to ſend this her beloved ſon out of the way from the fury of his brother <hi>Eſau;</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> for his own part to ſerve another Aprentiſhip, enjoying not the <hi>bleſſing,</hi> at leaſt in his own Land, till after much ſtrugling with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man</hi> to obtain it; yea, he had it not at all indeed, till God himſelf <hi>touched</hi> him in the <hi>hollow of his thigh,</hi> (that is to ſay) till he had loſt all ſtrength and confidence in carnall and worldly courſes, counſels and policies, and had nothing left him to reſt in but the naked <hi>will</hi> and <hi>preſence</hi> of God. For this cauſe he was made to <hi>halt,</hi> that it might be a ſigne to him of his former halting, and a caution to others to take heed of the like. This thing I deſire the preſent power of the Nation to take heed of, and lay to heart: they have indeed <hi>Jacob</hi>'s voice, talking much of <hi>God, Christ,</hi> the <hi>Spirit, Revelation, prayer, prophecie,</hi> the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> the higheſt form of knowledge, and talk of things divine is amongſt them: which if it be not in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>truth;</hi> that is to ſay, if it proceed not from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the true <hi>annoynting,</hi> and <hi>holy one</hi> among them, it is the moſt deceiving <hi>Antichrist</hi> that hath ever yet appeared in the world: and yet this I dare be bold to aver, that this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and talk of many of them (that I ſay not, the knowledge and talk of moſt) is but <hi>traditionall,</hi> and by imitation of others, having <hi>Chriſt</hi> in their mouth, but <hi>Sathan</hi> in their very <hi>hearts and lives,</hi> being, as the reſt of the world, <hi>holy by fits,</hi> holy now and then, holy upon <hi>Sundays,</hi> holy at a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> or a <hi>Sermon,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their ſeverall churches of which many are members, holy upon their dayes of <hi>fast</hi> and <hi>prayer;</hi> but not holy as every true Chriſtian is holy, <hi>in all manner of converſation,</hi> holy <hi>as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is holy;</hi> holy through their <hi>union</hi> with <hi>him,</hi> and enjoying of <hi>him.</hi> Theſe, theſe in the <hi>Army,</hi> God ſayes, <hi>They are a ſmoke in my noſe,</hi> a <hi>fire</hi> that <hi>burneth all the day:</hi> who being as ignorant in reſpect of pure and divine knowledge of God, and as full of enmity in their ſpirits againſt him as others, they condemn and ſay yet to others (in reſpect of themſelves) <hi>we are more holy then ye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>8</label> But yet I dare not, yea I ſhould grievouſly ſin againſt God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116119:22"/> and his preſence in the <hi>Army,</hi> ſhould I deny that there is the ſhout of a <hi>King,</hi> even of the <hi>King of Kings</hi> amongſt them; ſhould I deny that he hath given to many of them, yea ſome of the chief and top of them, to <hi>ſit together with him on his thron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> as the <hi>Father hath given him to ſit with him on his throne:</hi> theſe are they, to whom is given a pure language, not the <hi>language of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> or <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> no not of <hi>Samaria</hi> a mixt <hi>language,</hi> a language that is neer, or very like, but not the very language of heaven, or true Canaan: ſuch as is the language of the <hi>Jew,</hi> not ſuch a one that is ſo onely in the letter, and in reſpect of the outward man, but he that is ſo in the inward man, ſuch a one that ſpeaks ſuch a language that ſhall confound all other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; for <hi>thus ſaith the Lord of Hosts</hi> (the Lord of Armies) <hi>In thoſe days it ſhall come to paſſe, that ten men ſhall take hold</hi> (of all languages, ſuch as are the languages of the ſeverall Sects and ſorts of men among us) <hi>of the skirt of one,</hi> (ſuch a one that doth not onely <hi>ſay,</hi> but) that is a <hi>Jew,</hi> and of the ſeed of <hi>Jacob</hi> indeed, they ſhall take hold of the skirt of ſuch a one, ſaying, <hi>We will go with you, for we have heard that God is with you.</hi> This is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the voyce of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which I and all good men delight to hear among them, the <hi>joyfull ſound,</hi> the <hi>roaring</hi> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty like a Lion among you, whoſe preſence is terrible to the world: For becauſe of <hi>truth, meekneſſe</hi> (for <hi>the meek ſhall inherit the earth</hi>) and <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> (not that which is narrow and humane, but that which is divine and ſuperlative) <hi>he ſhall bring mighty things to paſſe.</hi> But as the Kingdom hears among you <hi>Jacob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> voyce (either pretended or in truth) ſo by feeling they finde your hands are too too much like <hi>Eſau</hi>'s hands, your little finger (in ſome regard) <hi>heavier then your fathers loins</hi> to the ſenſe of City and Country; the afflictions that have been and yet are upon them by the Parliament and their Proceedings and Armyes, are much more heavie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, and that upon both their friends and foes, then ever were the oppreſſions of the King and Prelates, reſpecting the outward man, upon that ſort of men that have now by a divine power got the upper hand of him. This is certain, the burthens of the people are many, and their fears are more,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116119:22"/> that one oppreſſing power will ſtill ſucceed another; ſo that the Land ſhall never enjoy her <hi>Sabbath,</hi> this I ſay, not to upbraid you, but to re-minde you that you fall not into the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and cenſure others did that went before you; <hi>for as their inward thought was, that their</hi> houſes <hi>ſhould continue for ever; and their dwelling places to generation and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they call their lands and their wayes after their names.</hi> Nevertheleſs, we ſee (one year after another) <hi>man,</hi> in <hi>true Chriſtian honour and integrity abideth not,</hi> but is like the <hi>beaſts that periſh being earthly,</hi> they ſink again into it: <hi>This their way is their folly, which too is made manifeſt ſooner</hi> or <hi>later:</hi> yet their poſterity, they that come after them in power and place, <hi>approve their ſayings,</hi> ſee a delight in their mouth, as it is in the margin; they have, as it were, <hi>one mouth,</hi> and <hi>are in effect the ſame in a new,</hi> and another ſeeming better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, the ſame Spirit appearing in another form; one evil generation and power of men oppoſing another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>9</label> 
                  <hi>The Lord therefore rebuke the evil</hi> Spirit <hi>that ſeeks</hi> to <hi>undoe,</hi> deceive and <hi>miſguide</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> into thoſe courſes that may any way tend to <hi>ſhut up</hi> the way of <hi>men</hi> to Chriſt their <hi>Savior,</hi> who is pretended to be among them more then among other people, and thoſe that went before them, that it may be ſaid of this King, (I mean not either <hi>King Charls,</hi> whoſe perſon yet I loved and prayed for) (or as the Country people ſpeak) King <hi>Fairfax</hi> or <hi>Cromwell,</hi> but <hi>King Jeſus;</hi> a King that is a Saviour, and in that he is a Saviour, a King; for every one worthy of the name, honor and title of a <hi>King,</hi> is a <hi>Saviour,</hi> a <hi>Saviour</hi> not only of his <hi>friends,</hi> but his very <hi>Enemies;</hi> King <hi>Charls</hi> would indeed have ſaved his friends (ſo, but corruptly called) but he being corrupt and ignorant of the true pattern [Chriſt] would fain have deſtroyed his (indeed but ſuppoſed) Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: let not the preſent <hi>Kingly power</hi> of the Nation in the <hi>Army,</hi> for there it is, interpretatively, and by way of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, let not them dance after his pipe, and do the thing he did, and have ſince condemned him for; that is to ſay, Let not them be the Saviours of their friends only, or men of one ſide, this is not the true <hi>Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> or of <hi>Government;</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116119:23"/> but let them even be <hi>Saviours</hi> to, and of thoſe, yea, even of <hi>thoſe</hi> that would in their ignorance and unbelief have deſtroyed them. This is truly <hi>noble, Chriſtian,</hi> and worthy of men of high place and power; let them be a <hi>Sanctuary</hi> of <hi>reſt</hi> to all, even the perſons of all Roundheads and Cavaliers, yet withall ſtanding as a <hi>Cherubin of light, right, truth, life, peace</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> to keep the way of that <hi>tree of Life,</hi> (a true <hi>Christian Magiſtracy,</hi> form'd according to the <hi>pattern</hi> in the <hi>Mount,</hi> whereby may be opened unto men that long expected and looked for <hi>paradiſe</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> meeting together, and giving reſt to the Nation;) and that no thing or perſon may be admitted, that may bring any evil into it, for the defilement and diſturbance of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>9</label> This, this is the buſineſs the preſent power have to doe, being reſerved and kept as in the <hi>ſecret of God</hi> to ſuch a time and purpoſe as this, that they might evidence to all, both friends and foes, that there is indeed ſuch a <hi>preſence of Christ,</hi> and the true <hi>anointing</hi> among them they have all this while held the world in hand with, that it may be ſaid of this <hi>Preſence,</hi> even of this <hi>Anointing</hi> among you, this <hi>King</hi> in the Army, to the whole Nation, on the one ſide and on the other, none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the grace and benediction of it; behold a <hi>King</hi> (God himſelf in Spirit) <hi>ſhall reign in righteouſneſſe;</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> (for ſuch are the children of the true <hi>Church</hi> in all lands) <hi>ſhall rule in Judgment;</hi> that is to ſay, not ignorantly and in the dark, not knowing what they doe, as the manner of the Rulers of the earth is, (being <hi>drunk</hi> with <hi>Error</hi> they <hi>ſtumble</hi> in Judgment;) <hi>then ſhall a man,</hi> (that is to ſay, every one that lives in the heavenly MAN) <hi>be for an hiding place,</hi> (what to one ſort of men only? that's <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> a courſe that hath undone us all this while, but to every man, though to the evil or luſt of no man) <hi>a hiding place, I ſay, from the wind,</hi> and a <hi>covert from the Tempeſt; as the rivers of water in a dry place:</hi> ſuch is for certain the ſtate of the Royall party, and in the next place the Presbyters and many others that are <hi>bitter</hi> and grieved in <hi>Spirit;</hi> in one word, as the <hi>ſhadow of a great rock in a weary Land,</hi> which how welcom it is in a Land of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116119:23"/> drought, as this Nation is, in reſpect of peace and reſt, they know, that have been by experience ſenſible of the one and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. By this it would appear to all the world, that you have skill not onely to kill, and to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> which hath been your work for the moſt part hitherto; but that you have <hi>heard and learned of the Father of mercies</hi> how to <hi>ſave:</hi> which is that one and onely thing the whole Kingdom is in expectation of from you: that it may be ſaid of you, <hi>Saviours</hi> (not deſtroyers) <hi>are come up upon Moun Sion, the true ſeat</hi> and place of Government, <hi>to judge the Mount of Eſau,</hi> that is to ſay, the evill of all men, by the <hi>ſpirit of judgement, and by the ſpirit of burning.</hi> Let the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and all in it firſt taſte of your <hi>good,</hi> that is to ſay, your <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, meekneſſe, forbearance, ſeeking not your own, but others profit,</hi> even the profit of your very <hi>oppoſers,</hi> whereby you wli lindeed appear to be of the <hi>onely true Royall bloud,</hi> even of the <hi>ſeed Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf: ſay, yea, you have much more cauſe to ſay of your ſelves then <hi>Saul</hi> had to ſay of himſelf, in the firſt day of his power, when the people came and clamoured in the ears of <hi>Samuel,</hi> as the people of England, ſo call'd, have of late in the ears of the Army, immoderately and to exceſſe, to have <hi>juſtice,</hi> not divine juſtice (for they know not, moſt of them, what that means) upon the perſon of the King, ſaying, <hi>Who is he</hi> of the King or Parliament's ſide, that <hi>ſaid,</hi> or ſhall ſay, <hi>Shall Saul reigne over us?</hi> Shall the <hi>Army</hi> power prevail over all ſorts of men in the Land (as you know, there is much mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring)? <hi>Bring the men, that we may put them to death.</hi> Let <hi>Saul</hi>'s Anſwer be yours, (I confeſſe, you pretend to a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to a better pattern, <hi>David,</hi> who though he were <hi>annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> to ſucceed <hi>Saul</hi> againſt whom there is no queſtion but <hi>David</hi> might have had as much to ſay, as you have had againſt <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> late in title King of <hi>England;</hi> yet <hi>David</hi> your pattern abhorred the thought of taking away his life, as you alſo, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the grounds of true Chriſtian Religion ought the forenamed and late King) <hi>And Saul ſaid, There ſhall not a man be put to death this day, for to day the Lord hath wrought ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Iſrael.</hi> Let not your morning glory, the glory you ſeek, be ſtained with the blood of any; eſpecially, the blood of war
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116119:24"/> in the time of peace: be not ſo haſty, hot and violent in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the Powers went before you, before your <hi>right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, integrity, innocency, honeſty, ability, impart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> and bowels of <hi>mercy, pity,</hi> and <hi>compaſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> toward the <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ</hi> be juſtified on all hands to be of a <hi>nature</hi> exceeding the pretence of others. Let the Kingly and Parliamentary Powers ſee, and the whole Kingdom with them, that you know as well how to mend faults, as to finde them out and puniſh them in o hers. In one word, Set up a <hi>high Court of grace, mercy,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vour</hi> (in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to, or <hi>union</hi> with this new <hi>high Court of Juſtice</hi>) to which all the afflicted and grieved in ſpirit may repair, and be relieved.</p>
               <p>This I humbly ſuggeſt, and lay it at the feet of Jeſus Chriſt among you, with whom I know it findes acceptance, for aſmuch as it is his minde, and the fruit of his <hi>annointing</hi> in me, by whom alone I have been able thus to ſpeak. He ſpeak it in you, even in the whole <hi>Army</hi> and Kingdom, that did endite and write it in my heart; which the everlaſting Spirit of grace work and grant, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116119:24"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is apparant, the late Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Army</hi> have awakened all ſorts of men to a more <hi>deep</hi> conſideration of the things <hi>past, preſent,</hi> and <hi>to come,</hi> relating to the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> At leaſt, I am ſure they have had this <hi>operation</hi> and <hi>effect</hi> on me, as may appear by the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of <hi>this</hi> — call it what you will, ſcarce the <hi>travell</hi> of two <hi>dayes:</hi> It may be thought of many, it had been <hi>better</hi> (as was deſired) to have had it <hi>ſtrangled</hi> in the <hi>birth;</hi> and the truth on 't is, had I conſulted mine own outward <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>acceptance</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>men,</hi> I ſhould have been <hi>first</hi> in laying hands on <hi>it.</hi> I beleeve there is ſo much <hi>truth</hi> in it, that it will almoſt <hi>offend</hi> all, though (if 'twere poſſible) I would not diſpleaſe <hi>any.</hi> I confeſſe, I perceive in the ARMY much more of the <hi>Souldier yet,</hi> then of the <hi>Christian,</hi> as there did appear in the Powers <hi>before,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116119:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116119:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116119:26"/> more of the <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> then of <hi>Christ</hi> or the new <hi>Creature.</hi> I have therefore, as <hi>Moſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from the <hi>Mount</hi> (though I would not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute any thing to my ſelf) who <hi>brake</hi> in pieces the two <hi>Tables,</hi> of which the people in <hi>his</hi> abſence, or rather, in the abſence of GOD, made an <hi>Idoll, made a Calf</hi> (I beleeve the Nation hath done little elſe theſe many yeers;) I ſay, I have not (as hee) ſpared mine <hi>owne fleſh,</hi> mine own <hi>People,</hi> mine own <hi>Intereſts</hi> on the one hand, or the other. I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in it many <hi>Erratas;</hi> ſome happening through the neglect (though voluntary, not <hi>mine</hi>) of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon intended to bring it forth to <hi>cenſure;</hi> which was indeed before the fall of the <hi>late Great KING;</hi> yea, purpoſed, according to its <hi>ſtrength,</hi> (which was (and you ſee is) but as the ſtrength of a <hi>little childe</hi>) to ſtand in the way of that <hi>ſpirit</hi> that conſented to the putting him to death; hence mention is made <hi>confuſedly</hi> of him, ſometimes as <hi>living,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>gone.</hi> Secondly, others, not a few, occaſioned through my abſence from the Preſſe.</p>
            <p>I have but two things more to take out of the way, that I <hi>offend</hi> none.</p>
            <p n="1">1. My ſugeſting mine <hi>own apprehenſion</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>preſence</hi> with the <hi>King</hi> in the day of his <hi>affliction;</hi> which I judge was much with <hi>Him</hi> for his <hi>ſupport:</hi> What others attribute to the power of Nature, and a <hi>Roman-like Spirit</hi> (as they ſpeak) that I give to the <hi>immediate mighty power</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, My <hi>offending</hi> the preſent <hi>Power:</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116119:26"/> To this I anſwer, 1. I have ſaid nothing to <hi>offend</hi> it; but (as much as in me is) to <hi>rectifie</hi> it. 2. They are but even now <hi>come forth;</hi> and it will be for their further <hi>clearing,</hi> to ſcoure <hi>off</hi> what is <hi>droſſe</hi> and <hi>filth</hi> among them. Laſtly, they <hi>themſelves,</hi> even ſome of the <hi>top men among them,</hi> profeſſe they <hi>act much</hi> in the <hi>dark</hi> in theſe things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
